so I had a question about
upana often translated as
assumption the whole idea behind the
kind of translation of assumption is
that that it is something that you're
not really even aware of so somebody who
doesn't know they're adopted just
assumes that they're not adopted yeah
it's not even on their radar as a view
they hold until they're confronted with
something that indicates otherwise yeah
so how could you possibly get to the
point where you are Beyond
assumptions which is the state of the AR
how can you know that there's nothing
that you're assuming anymore seems like
an impossible
well it would seem impossible
if
uh that's actually a common thing that
the truth is thought of as a some sort
of um external on some sort of external
level like
uh practicing the dhama to find out the
truth meaning some some sort of Med
physical principle that underlies
universe or something and then on that
level yes you will never be sure that
you understood everything uh so it's I
mean technically uh the dhama is not
really um at least not in the sense that people
um at least not in the sense that people
think of reality like finding out the
truth of reality because uh yeah that
notion of reality is really not what the
Buddha was talking about it's not the
five Aggregates it's some external
assumption to your five Aggregates of
some kind of external principle that
underlies other people and that you can
be aware of independently of your point
of view
so you would know that you're free from
assumption first of all by understanding
the level where assumptions are which is
in regard to your own uh
relationship with any ideas about the
truth of real it for example like uh
assumptions would happen in regard to
you thinking about
this while you're thinking about what
the truth of reality is philosophizing
about that stuff there would be
assumptions there on that internal level
that matters so what is the mo most
fundamental assumption that uh this is just talk
assumption that uh this is just talk
about for example because uh that's
another thing it's not like assumption
assumption in general the Buddha said
there are four types of assumtions it's
not apart from that so right well like
to kind of use that example again of the
adopted it's not like when you become an
Aran you like find out you're actually
adopted like it's it's not on that level
of things yeah um but to answer your
question self viw yeah so assumption
self viw meaning you assume
that things belong to you that's that's
the fundamental assumption so even when
you contemplate and not everything by the
contemplate and not everything by the
way it's not like um truth of anata is
about finding out
that things out there like every
Mountain I see every wall I see every uh
I don't know block of wood I see I need
to remind myself that it's anata no
there are things that are that you
already recognize this is not mine but
the assumption is specifically
in regard to those more personal things
in your own experience what are those
personal things well uh form feeling
perception intention and Consciousness
that's where the assumption is
so you would know that you're free from
assumption first of all
by well by by knowing what assum first
of all you find out what assumption is
you get the right view that's the the
first the first uh like uh Milestone
that you need to see so what is that
Assumption of
self is it just holding a
belief like consciously that things are
mind yeah perhaps you should clear up
whether there's a distinction between
let's say belief opinions and
assumptions because assumptions is
basically on the level of you
right so we're not just talking about
opinions and beliefs yeah we right
because that you can easily change yeah
um yeah exactly like almost every
dedicated Buddhist already has the
belief that there is no self the belief
of another essentially yeah that then
becomes another problem yeah and and yet
they're not free from suffering so how
can that that's clearly then as you said
it's not on the same level assumption
and belief not is not on the same level
yeah so that is genely the case and now
in particular we should clear up that
the Buddha actually never really taught
like almost the metaphysical statement
there is no self his teaching is about
recognizing how things are not self yeah
and that is not just like oh whether you
add a t to the no or not that is just
splitting airs no no this is a very
fundamental difference because to start
out by saying there is no self is in a
sense already the now of the problem
whereas one once it's clear that the whole
one once it's clear that the whole
problem is to realize that things are
not self then it is about how you are
regarding things yeah exactly and that's
um when when people would think it's
about the belief of self like this
metaphysical almost uh concept how do
you define the self people would think
it's about that uh but yeah like you
said the Buddha never discussed it in
those terms it's actually you have a
sense of of self because you take things
as yours not like first you start with
the sense of self that you have to
Define in such and such away and then
because that self exists then that self
takes things up it's the other way
around so that's why whenever the Buddha
would talk about not self he would
emphasize form is not self feeling is
not self um perception is not self
intentions is not self consciousness is
not self so anything that you would take
to self would have to be one of those
five things and so by seeing that
nothing can
self on that level you don't need to
care one bit about defining what the
self is you will know that because you
no longer take the entirety of experien
in mind which is the five arrogates then
there is no sense of self so that's the
assumption is like um that's really what
the assumption is it's not like uh I
have a wrong belief like if I ask you
what is the self and you you gave me a
wrong answer or something that's not
what the what uh wrong view means it
means taking on on any level any aspect of
taking on on any level any aspect of
your experience as mine so you
assume like if you have a I don't know
something that actually the Buddha gave
a simil like a like a borrowed
jewelry and uh you may not even know
that it's borrowed so you assume that
it's yours and you act with it as if
it's yours and then suddenly you know I
don't know let's say you went to a party
or something and you're wearing old
jewelry and getting a lot of pleasure
out of it and then suddenly you see the
person who is the actual owner of the
jewelry and he takes it away right at
that moment
so you that's practically speaking you
were assuming that that jewelry is yours
and it's the same with the five
Aggregates it's like uh everything can
go well for quite a while but the fact
that the state of Affairs is contrary to
how you assume it to be in this case
that it does belong to you uh eventually
it will become clear that uh it's not
actually the case
because at some point um something you
don't want will be experienced some
something you want will fade away and uh
that's that's how your assumption is
proved wrong so how would you know that
there is no assumption well
again not by um thinking of it in those
abstract terms like could I get the idea
about what not self is
wrong but by asking
yourself who is there any
possibility that if things change in any
way in any uh
direction that I even that I might not
expect or it hasn't happened before that
I would suffer that's a measure of
whether there is assumption or not
whether there is something that could make you
there is something that could make you
suffer
and it's not even um like uh it's not
like you can deceive yourself about
this like if you're if you're if you
have a basic sense of a authenticity as
we discussed
before you need very little reflection
actually to
see that there is still suffering and so
that's your measure of the Assumption
not like how your beliefs are on a
conceptual level but how possible is it
that suffering might arise for me and
the size of your assumption is the size
of
um how much suffering there could be and
how many things could cause it right so
on account of
um reducing the size of that that
assumption the size of the suffering
will Al would also decrease so that's
like the
Noble disciples uh they still have some degree
disciples uh they still have some degree
of assumption but it can never
be nearly the same amount as auga so
that's why as said the it's like seven
grains of sand
for that is the SI the the the size of
the Assumption compared to the size of
the pist assumption the Assumption
itself so yeah seven grains of sand
compared to the whole Himalayas yeah
yeah yeah so that's the if there there
is suffering there has H sorry if there
is assumption there has to be suffering
if there is suffering there has to be
assumption so that's that's really your
measure so then uh if you have developed
that criteria of authenticity that we
discussed before
then you know for sure how to
investigate your
liability you know how to see whether
you're liable to something or not and uh
yeah that that's how asking
yourself death for example sickness
aging like people usually think of the
practice as some sort of
um uh these mystical truths that you
discover that very pleasant to find out
how your Consciousness is constantly
changing every second or something but
the the dhama starts with the Buddha
himself he went forth because he wanted
to find the way out of sickness aging
and death mhm not because you wanted to
find out these very the ultimate truths
of the universe yeah yeah so that is
that is the everything that that he
taught assumption ignorance all of that
pertains to that liability to sickness
aging and death so any person who even a
sop or anagami even if they reflect
properly they would be able to see
just by thinking by reflecting oh are
there things that could could cause
suffering in this mind and the answer
will have to be yes um so it's really
about like uh developing that self
transparency so that your questioning of
your liability to suffering is accurate
and based on that you indirectly know
okay there is assumption
left now ordinar to to few would be I
exist and then because I exist I have
desire for this and I regard things like
that but you just said that actually
Assumption of self is secondary it is
the product of taking things as mine so
in order to Upper root that assumption
can we explore in more detail how what
is involved in regarding things as mine
because when that becomes more clear the
result will be that there is no longer
room for Assumption of self so what is
then practically involved in regarding
things as mine what does that
mean well not
to attending rightly things so
not recognizing or Discerning the the
womb of things or attending without
Yar so in this way you
basically take the experience beginning
of the
experience from the point of yeah first
is I am the first one and I'm attending
to anything out
there so that would be the wrong wrong
type of attention is there something
more concrete you before
concrete you before
that oh in terms of uh you mean like
precepts and yeah yeah so yeah you have
to basically prepare
the the ground for it so to speak like
keeping the precepts oral precepts and uh
the precepts oral precepts and uh
restraining your acting out of
pressure so is it by acting out of
pressure is it by acting out of pressure
that one is practically regarding things
as mine like can you act out of pressure
without you already regarding things as
mine
or does every acting out of pressure
necessarily implies imply that thing
that you take things to be yours
yeah so it's uh even like pressure and
you can sort of particularize it into
passion aversion and distraction the
acting out of pressure so you know that
if you have such
actions with no regard whatsoever for
your abstract ideas about not self you
have a sense of self like by committing
those actions so actually that's an
important thing I I forgot to bring up
the Buddha said um in
W he he talked about 11 things that if
you don't understand it's impossible for
you to make progress in the Dharma MH
this is the I think
it's ma 33 or 34 he said um one of them
was abiku does not understand a fool is
determined by his actions and the wise
person is determined by their actions MH
so because it sounds like okay sure but
if you think about it many people would
actually Overlook that they would think
you can have wisdom by you know having
these abstract sort of very mystical
ideas about emptiness and and not self
and how Consciousness changes and you
know the the Mind moments and the train
of stream of Consciousness or whatever
all all of which is already little to do
with the D just to be clear yeah but at
the same time then they continue to act
out of passion aversion in delusion so
from that point of view according to the
Buddhist definition that person remains
a fool just as much because they are
acting like a fool is determined by his
actions a wise person is determined by
his actions so person who understands
anata is is uh would be determined by
the actions that they do more
importantly then by what that that
that's really what's
revealing your assumptions like what
what actions you do rather than uh your
intellectual what you say yeah yeah
exactly yeah because that's even also
like way of uh recognizing a good
teacher yes you have to stay live with
him for a long time and that's also from
the sutas where you have to stay for a
long time and see him in different
situations yeah when when he's being
praised or criticized and you know
basically he's being challenged only
then on account of basically seeing him
in this in this different
uh uh pressing situations you can judge
okay now I can see that there is a I
can't see grieved there or mhm AV verion
yeah you can catch some glimpse of that
but you see now you say a fool is
determined by his actions and a wise
person is determined by his actions but
somebody comes along and says well I
thought no disciple who understands not
self so how can there be any action when
there is no longer self so how can a
wise person someone who understands not
self how can there still be action
defining that individual how right
that's a very an idea but it's not
accurate so if we want to um go go into
the truth of the statement that the fool
is determined by his actions and a wise
person is determined by his
actions um if this is not going to give
rise to those kind of uh questions we
should perhaps say something more about
it yeah so see that would already be
coming from the same kind of mystical
idea like not self means like oh there's
no there's nobody here or something yeah
like like nobody is acting everything is
just happening you didn't decide to do
anything at all it's just the
spontaneous activity of the universe and
that's precisely or you can say oh it's
just Consciousness arising and passing
or something and you read the sutas and
it seems like you're saying the same
thing but then it's contradicting the
same the very statement because then the
said there are things that the Arun is
incapable of doing on account of the
freedom from G verion delusion he didn't
say oh Arun uh you know there's no Arun
so this is not really this is not really
happening or something they these
actions don't exist no it says there are
things that he he is incapable of doing
M and um it also says uh actually in
another Su it says here a person might
see um or might think oh he is
restrained out of because he's
restrained because he's not free he's
he's remains in seclusion because he's
still not free he's uh dedicated to to
um you know virtue because he's still
not free but uh the the S says No it
should not be seen that way it's because
um he's intent on the absence of
attachment basically
mhm speaking about Anar so it's not
saying like he has no choice to to you
know it's just a process or something
it's saying that he's choosing to still
be restrained still keep the virtue
still do these things on account of a
preference for non-attachment preference
for non- craving and all and all this so
it's not like
um cuz
see you would with that view actually
even the what we usually call the
mundane Right View mhm it would be like
you become an Arun by really saying
there is no action there is no no fruits
uh of good and bad actions there is no
mother there is no father that's
essentially with with the view of uh
freedom is but no you have to reach
Freedom while still recognizing and
taking on that there is action there is
results it is you who is doing this not
not somebody else like it's not
happening by itself or any of this so
actually kind of by trying to shortcut
into the the what you think the right
you is you actually end up somewhere
completely different yeah that's right
so which is happening a lot in the name
of well Buddhism yeah so this is why I
thought we could spend some time
dwelling on these on these on these
wrong ideas so the so the difficulty is
then to see how can that be
action uh against the background of the
truth of not self yeah because say the
the the when the Buddha talked about
being free from K doesn't mean again in
this mystical sense of like there is
action but really there is no action or
something like that it's it's uh when he
explained why is uh form impermanent why
is uh perception impermanent he said
it's because if you were well in order for it
because if you were well in order for it
to be self you would have to be able to
say may my form be like this may my form
not be like this may my feeling be like
this may my feeling not be like this
that was clearly the second um this
course he gave so it is it's not that
there is no self again because of this
metaphysical truth that things are not
real or something it's because of the
lack of control that you have over
things so you would see um absence of
action would be through the
understanding that even if you do
something that's being done because form
feeling perception intention and
Consciousness is allowing you to do this
mhm so it's kind of like
um like you know in the past with the
self viw you would have believed that
you yourself were the one making you
know moving things around to put it that
way but now it's not like there is no
movement it's like every time you want
to do something you actually have to
submit a
proposal and then your boss is the one
who does it mhm and but before you
assume that no it's like direct kind of
like I make a choice and then the result
comes about like that but you understand
actually there's a middleman there mhm
that you were kind of missing and uh
because most of the time things went as
you planned like you wanted pleasure and
you managed to get it you wanted pain
and you managed to avoid it you forgot
that there's actually a middleman there
between you wanting something and the
result actually coming about and it's
the AR it's like it's the the
impermanence of of or the uncertainty of
these things makes makes it so that it's
not that you will never get what you
want like factually there are times
where you can achieve your wishes but
the thing is it always goes through that
middle then and because of that if you
understand that you'll be able to
understand oh there is no
um like um it's
unjustifiable it actually does me much
more harm than good to assume myself to
D to be able to
directly exert control over things but
there is that relative degree of control
so to speak so then um because otherwise
there will be no path no practice no
Freedom yeah and and then also like the
AR would be like some sort of
robot uh functioning on deterministic
principles or something MH but the like
becoming art just become something ROM
that we can choose and as well it would
be uh some people actually in even in
the Buddhist time they he said some
people misrepresent me by saying that I
teach the annihilation of an existing
being M be like you know you you hear that
M be like you know you you hear that
statement and you might think oh so
they're explicitly saying like oh you're
annihilationist but really
annihilationism is also included in this
very view that by supposedly
understanding anata like it now it's
just a process and uh it's just uh
happening happening yeah so that is
annihilationism literally like you had a
self before and through this practice
you made it so that now there's only a
process so you
annihilated the existing being that was
there and the Buddha said some people
misrepresent me by saying that's that's
my teaching MH and that's exactly what
what happens even today like people
would think it's kind of I had a self
before and then through this practice I
and then through this practice I
destroyed it basically so but no the
sense of
self um it's not a it's not on that
level like I said it's it's that
Assumption of um that direct the right
control but when you when you abandon it
when you abolish it um there is still an
individual as Buu Saida is the word for
individual individual so
um there is still a kind of um I mean
that's why AR Hans would have different
Tendencies for example like uh you know
mahaka for example he wanted to stay in
the forest the Buddha seemed to come
with him to live in the more comfortable
environment and he said no and then
whenever you know various events and
stuff happened he was always like quite
abrasive and uh had a different
different uh temperament temperament
for example so or one of them the first
disciple he he was so uh like
disillusioned with this this idea of
more people like he was fond of his seclusion
people like he was fond of his seclusion
so much basically then as soon as he
became an AR he left and he didn't see
the Buddha for like 20 years M uh and
then there were other Arad who were you
know quite happy to help out the new
monks and stuff so if if it were just
like some sort of um again
deterministic like deletion
of of uh the individual basically then
uh character yeah if your character then
there there would have to be um all the
same all the same Army of the same
arkans yeah so this middle man that you
were talking about that is the five
agates themselves basically yeah yeah so
it's like
so so everything that assumed five gets
ahuh so okay so that that raises
question is there still a middleman in
the ous case no like fully understanding
that there is a middleman is how you
would been the Assumption yeah that's
like the the assumption is the direct
yeah of the yeah so how so how can
one reflect on that wisely like um so
everything that you you want to do that
is to say every intention that you think
is yours is Possible only because
because you find yourself in a wider
situation that allows you to attend in
that way so so your intentions are never
in isolation like oh I want to go and
make a tea well that's possible only be
because there happens to be a kitchen
with a cattle and tea and all and all
the rest of it and there's this body so
so that intention has to be seen as
fully embedded within the totality of
this evision experience
but but when that intention is taken as
my intention in that direct sense that
entire context is is being overlooked
and the intention is being seen in
isolation and and that is how it never
exists yeah so just just tell tell
somebody who whose legs got amputated to
start walking they can't so it's like even us
walking they can't so it's like even us
healthy people we can do stuff because
the body allows you to do it first but
then you might develop all sorts of
Notions again my body and all this and
see having views that this is not my
body that doesn't in and of itself if
you don't see why it's not my body if
you just apply this view which is what
usually happens like um that that's not
making any difference because it's like
you you just in the same way that
somebody would believe in God or
something and through that conviction
you you just pasted over everything MH
well now it's it's a similar principle
you're just pasting this ideal which
could have been anything else really mhm
over over things like this is not mine
but it's you you there no reason for it
no you just accept that view and you're
applying it to everything but you need
to understand why is it that things are
not mine and like recognize it yeah
realizing because D is apparent here now
so that's not something you have to kind
of explain yourself or yeah so it exists
for you as a view but actually you find
things in this way yeah that way yeah
and not and it would have to be not like
um cuz really that's the implication
like before when I didn't know about
this things were different now that I
know about this mystical truth of anata
now things are like that because it is a
a kind of um fabricated IDE drived idea
so it's not it it doesn't fit the
criteria of the dama being directly
visible as the budha said because there
was like tell a farmer or something that try
like tell a farmer or something that try
to talk to a farmer now let alone in in
you know ancient India about how his
mind is is composed of 52 different
types of Mind moments and every single
one is constantly changing then try to
tell him you know give an explanation of
that and see if he would actually tell
you oh yeah this is directly
visible no and in fact that's just
another mystical assumption this whole
idea that things change or flicker in
and out of existence very quickly more
quickly than than you can manage to keep
track of with your mindfulness or with
your awareness or something therefore it
only appears as if things endure but
behind the scene I that's the difference
between appearance and the and the
Ultimate Reality then they really
flicker in and out of resistance and
then the whole practice of meditation
becomes to gain a certain speed of your
mindfulness in order to observe the gaps
of things flickering in out it that's
full-blown mystical view yeah and see
that's not directly visible no that's
not direct yes but you see but then
people will say no no I I need to have
very deep meditation so that that
mystical truth becomes directly visible
to me but see that that didn't so that
didn't exist like you you brought this
thing about yeah that was not there
before doesn't include you because you
are still that kind of you know Observer
yeah your point from outside looking at
it yeah so um yeah that's I wanted to
get into that as well
so the the view of of impermanence um
suffering M
self if impermanence is taken as this uh
like you said things flickering in and
out of existence then it's easy to
explain oh so so means like there is no
self because if everything is Con
constantly changing there is no identity
of things like nothing Remains the Same
but again you don't find a single suta
where the Buddha explained not self in
those terms he always used the the
analogy of or or the metaphor of um
trying to control something like he gave
the Sim of if you would find random
sticks and branches in the forest and
then somebody would come and burn them
and then would you be like uh affected
in thinking oh why are you burning us
why are you burning me on account like
by them burning those sticks and you
would say no in the same way you should
regard your own Aggregates
so uh not because they don't exist and
they're flickering in and out of
existence but again because of the lack
of lack of control yeah so um even if
you could see them flickering in and out
of existence like even if you could have
that vision you're still going to take
that flickering in and out of existence
as you you like there is an exertion of
of assumption of control there like U if
you haven't understood the sense of self
for what it is then you might very well
be having you know well most of the time
it would be like that like you
you're there is a exertion of that
assumed intention without that middleman
as I just mentioned towards you getting
that vision of things constantly
changing like uh you don't see for
example that even that experience of
seeing things constantly changing
depends on having a healthy body having
a healthy mind having you know not being
dead you don't see that middleman so the
Assumption of self is very much still
there because you think you have um like
I mean just imagine you got this vision
of the constant flux of things and
everything makes sense and you're
enlightened now and then tomorrow you
don't have it
you just happen to forget yeah so then
if you suffered on account of that means
that was not not s that you not seeing
that because it had to lead to freedom
from any sort of appropriation yeah and
then you're going to exert yourself in
order to get that experience again yeah
so there that right there is the
Assumption of control I want may my
perception be thus may my Consciousness
be th and that is the assumtion of self
right there so that's anti Mission the
points and even if there would be stuff
flickering in in and out of the
assistance in order to even that can
that itself can never be outside the
five Aggregates yeah yeah so then so you
see it just those so that is just not it
doesn't add up basically so so
um the what I wanted to to get to as
well is that these three characteristics
oh before I get into that actually so
you wouldn't see from this uh sequence
like things constantly changing
therefore um they have no lasting
identity but where's the dook part yeah
so there is no inherent uh suffering in
the fact that uh you have Perpetual
novelty because the Buddha said
suffering is because of
anicha so how is it that suffering would
be a natural conclusion of this flux it
it just doesn't follow MH because in
order for you to suffer on account of
the impermanence of things there needs
to have been some sort of um
lasting of that thing yeah otherwise
like how can you talk about the thing
that I'm attached to which might change
mhm so yeah so so you would never would
have become attached to something if it
wasn't on account of regarding that
thing as permanent yeah and and but if
that thing didn't endure for more than a
My Moment how could you have the veloped
the attachment in the first place and
then but then there comes all this sort
of uh Patchwork just saying like well
yeah the attachment you have multiple
mind moments of attachment following one
one after the other but that's like yeah
then you can just further down that same
Rabbit Hole it just yeah that's not how
it works yeah so
so the the point is as i' kept repeating
the dhama is directly visible so
everyone the anas duata that the Buddha
is talking about is something that the
Buddha that everyone already sees
because it's he doesn't say the noble
one he just understands it says no ones
understands all Saras are an all Saras
are du or Damas are not self but this
not everybody sees no but everybody sees
everybody can see this is impermanent
this is suffering this is not mine you
mean some object in the world yeah
something some specific thing but what
they cannot see is
there's the other one as well everything
that is of the nature of arising is of
the nature of ceasing yeah that's the
understanding that actually takes you
well that's what qualifies as
Enlightenment so anicha is not like you
to see the Ana itself there is nothing
like you know um rocket science about it
it's you see a
tree uh and you know that it's liable to
die at some point M but the problem is
there are things in your own experience
that you don't see having that same
nature as that tree meaning your form
your body your feelings your perceptions
your intentions your Consciousness so
even if you give everything up like you
you live under a bridge or something and
you never eat and you don't do anything
when your perceptions change you will
still be affected as if this thing was
supposed to last forever mhm so so
that's what uh you you can't see the
entirety of your
experience as impermanent as suffering
as not self but the the concept of uh
impermanent suffering not self is really
nothing like uh uh but wait but the
noble disciple can see the entirety of
experience as yeah yeah so what I'm
saying is that is the work that is what
the pujian is lacking being able to see
the entirety of the experience in that
way like he already knows what an NAD
duata is in a mundane sense but he
doesn't see it in regard to form feeling
perception well he doesn't even see the
Aggregates to begin with yeah so how
that that really is the work like how do
I recognize the Aggregates and
then uh these three characteristics will
become apparent yeah immediately so
first one needs to apprehend what these
agcat are right as you just mentioned
because otherwise how is it possible to
start regarding them as Ana Dua andata
if that phenomena has not been
designated correctly then then even if
you do it sort of rightly it will still
be too Limited in order to bring about
the the the the the Insight of entering
the path so it's it's not um it's not
like usually again the tendency would be
okay I'm meditating and making all this
effort so I get to understand what an
really is but no it's what you need to
do is uncover like what your experience
is in the first place so that it becomes
apparent that this is an so that's what
the signs of the mind that this that the
Su talk about that would be revealed
only on account of
seclusion because well in seclusion you
get to see actually the Buddha said that
based a who is secluded obviously there
is seclusion by body and mind but uh in
the su he just used the word secluded
and he saidu included what does he see
he sees such as the arising of form such
as the sensation of form such as the
arising of feelings such as sensation of
feeling but again if you think it's this
very complex mind moments of these
things constantly changing no it's you
are sitting there having thoughts about
this about that
and that right there is already the
Aggregates not like you need to take
this microscope and start looking harder
it's already there right now as we're
talking form is arising form is ceasing
so it's it's um on the level really of
more General rather than focusing harder
in particular moments so it's uh you
will get to see okay how do I see
feeling what is feeling
so how do I feel
now Pleasant unpleasant neutral
mhm so this feeling now now I have
various attitude towards it I want to
get rid of it I want to get more of it
if it's
pleasant but did I did I not have a
different feeling
yesterday and I was also trying to get
rid of it and I was also trying to get
more of it so then oh so that's what
feeding is it's not something uh
mystical it's right there and
then if it's clearly happening that like
I always want my feelings to remain
Pleasant I never want them to if if
feedings were obeying my will an
unpleasant feeling would never have
Arisen in the first place so then see
that's already closer to a reflection of
on Anish duata but for as long as the
person hasn't gone the Right View well
it's because not because of the anicha
part but because well okay you saw some
extent of feeling but uh there's always
more layers of it to be revealed
for example so that's really what uh
what you would have to emphasize like
how to recognize my experience as a
whole not particular mind moments but
this experience now sitting
here that's where you would find these
these characteristics
so and that's how like without having
to um
have special meditation sessions or
something every day to practice this you
would be able to
remain with the perspective of anad
duata even though when you're going
around U doing work or something that
that takes all of your attention you
don't have time to be watching the
moments flickering in and out but you do
know that that same experience as a
whole that was there when you were alone
reflecting like I mentioned well that
same experience as a whole is there now
it's the same thing so but if it if it
were about this watching these um you
know esoteric phenomena well that's not
going to be there anymore when you come
out of your when you open your eyes
basically it's not going to be there
anymore so that that applied to a very
limited scope e